Hi, this is Dr. Maria Plummer,
and this lecture is on
myocardial infarction and
a little bit of an overlap
with the lecture on
atherosclerosis because we're
gonna talk a little bit
about ischemic heart disease.
It's part of a spectrum,
and at one point,
these lectures were
two hours long in
one sitting, but
we've divided them up.
Okay, so these are the
session objectives,
and as you can tell,
objectives one and two, we
kind of already discussed
in atherosclerosis and
ischemic heart disease, but
we'll review it briefly.
So this is the outline.
We're reviewing ischemic
heart disease. I'm not
going to talk in myocardial
infarction too much about
the EKG changes. I'll
leave that to the cardiologists
who know it better,
but we will talk about
the pathophysiology, the
gross and microscopic
changes and complications
along with scattered practice
questions throughout.
So the ischemic heart
disease syndromes
include myocardial
infarction which is obviously
the worst where
basically ischemia causes
necrosis or death of
the cardiac muscle.
Angina or angina
pectoris is pain in the
chest which could be
stable or unstable.
Usually ischemia in
those cases aren't severe
enough, but it can be a
precursor to MI. And then
there's chronic ischemic
heart disease with heart
failure and, of course,
sudden cardiac death.
We're really going to
talk mostly about, in this
lecture, myocardial
infarction. So as discussed,
myocardial ischemia can
result in stable angina,
which means chest pain with
physical activity. And we
talked about coronary
artery stenosis about 70-75%
although different books
may say different things.
Unstable angina is chest
pain at rest or progressively
worsening chest pain over
time and principal angina
is usually referring to
a vasospasm especially in
cocaine use although you
do have some vasospasm even
in other anginas. myocardial
infarct and sudden
cardiac death. Okay I want
to really emphasize that in
myocardial infarction there
is an acute plaque change
and that from a
vulnerable plaque remember
vulnerable plaques easily
ruptured and what happens is
there's total thrombotic
occlusion and so if you stop
the blood flow in the
coronary artery to that area
of myocardial tissue you
will get myocardial death.
Over 90% of patients
who have ischemic heart
disease of any type will
have atherosclerosis,
one or often more coronary
arteries. And we discussed
the obstructions again,
70-75% would be induced
by exertion, symptoms
induced by exertion, whereas
90% usually at rest. But
what's in red there is
really a real take-home
point in that the number
one source of MI is acute
plaque rupture of vulnerable
or unstable plaque
with thrombus formation
and that is shown in the
cartoon down below and that
is really the important
thing to take away here.
So when we say infarction
of any type of myocardial
infarction we're talking
about necrosis or death of
cardiac myocytes. It's
irreversible and most likely it's
due to rupture of an
atherosclerotic plaque with a
superimposed thrombus. Now
here is his leading cause
of death in the U.S. and
that is was true it is true
I just read an article
literally last week saying
that it may not be the leading
cause of death other heart
diseases may because
we've been so good about
treating it but it is a big
cause of death nevertheless.
Okay so initially when
you have is necrosis
it's going to start in
the subendocardium and
that means less than
50 percent of the
myocardial thickness and
when you do have that
you'll have st segment
depression on the ekg
as it continues you'll get
transmural necrosis which
involves the entire
thickness and then there's st
segment elevation on the
ekg now these pictures are
gross pictures and really
they're not a hundred percent
you can't really see exactly
the endocardium but let
me see if I can outline
for you here this is the
subendocardium up that's
not working okay this is the
subendocardium here okay
and you see this bread with
stuff that's the area of
necrosis whereas down here
the whole wall pretty much
is affected by this pale.
I mean it doesn't always
have to be red, it could be
pale, but this is most of
the thickness of the wall.
So that's transmural and
that's the takeaway here.
Okay I
am trying to get this to go,
okay here we go, all right
let's see if we can erase this.
So as I said transmural MI,
which really is the most
common type of MI, involves
the full thickness of
the ventricular wall. And
in whatever distribution
of whatever coronary artery,
we'll talk about that
in a little bit, it is
associated with coronary
atherosclerosis, coronary
artery disease, because of
acute plaque change and
superimposed thrombosis.
Yes, I am repeating myself
because that's important.
Whereas sub-endocardial
infarct is an area of
necrosis that's limited
to the inner half or the
inner third of the ventricular
wall. NB is a Latin
term meaning note bene,
which is please note.
The reason why the
subendocardium is the first
to suffer in an infarct,
it's the least well
perfused. Because if you
remember, the coronary
arteries are in the
epicardium, in the epicardial
adipose tissue, and
they penetrate through
the wall. So the
subendocardium is the most
vulnerable to reduction in
coronary blood flow okay
now the clinical features
the typical are the very
um you know usually the
ones you read in book is a
severe chest pain crushing
uh feels like an elephant
on the chest and by
definition it lasts you
know usually more than 15 or
20 minutes it may radiate
to the left side of the
neck the jaws the arms and
other symptoms may include
diaphoresis or sweating
and shortness of breath,
fatigue, nausea, vomiting,
and also a sense of
impending doom. People
have this been described
as saying this and also
fainting or syncope.
The symptoms are going to not
be relieved by nitroglycerin.
So somebody's had angina
and it helped and now
it's not going to help. You
could also get silent MIs
and that occurs in patients
or in individuals with
diabetes and elderly because
the pain threshold is different.
And also in women the
symptomatology may be
different. Okay now where does
this MIs usually occur? Well
most of them occur or a
good portion of them occur
in the left ventricular anterior
wall, and that's because
most MIs are caused by
an occlusion of the left
anterior center artery, also
known as the widow's artery,
because normally this does
cause death, and it's also
the anterior septum and
the apex circumferentially.
That's 40 to 50 percent of
cases. In about 30 to 40
percent, the second most
commonly involved artery is
right coronary artery, which
means that the posterior
wall will be infarcted or
the posterior septum and also
the papillary muscles.
And rarely you may have an
occlusion of the left
circumflex artery, which means
lateral wall of the left
ventricle, except for the apex.
Okay, so this is a very
simplified view of EKG
changes. I am not going
to go into all the EKG
changes because You have
very good lectures and
discussions by cardiologists
who really go in detail
about EKG. And I'm a
pathologist, and usually
I do not read EKGs. But
I do want to say that as
a ST or STEMI-MI evolves,
this is what you see.
The ST elevation is
in a wide, large T,
occurs very acutely.
and after 1 to 14 hours,
you develop the
persistence of the ST
elevation and you start
developing the Q wave.
And then, of course, in
phase 3, after 12 to 24 hours
from MI onset, you're
going to have ST elevation
subsiding and the Q wave
becomes deeper, T inversion
becomes deeper, QT prolongs.
All these specifics
are going to be covered in
EKG lectures. and remember
that after a while when
the even after the ST
changes if the person survives
may disappear the Q wave
remains present to indicate
an old MI okay so this
is just a general simplified
way the MI diagnosis
is made clinically and by
EKG and biochemically now
being a pathologist I
think that the biochemical
markers are most important.
Having said that, you
don't always, you can't wait
for the biochemical markers
at all, all the time.
So the EKG changes, it's
going to be very important
to be able to read them.
Biochemical markers to me
tell me the truth in that
the tissue has died and
released these enzymes.
Whereas if somebody places
EKG leads the wrong way, or
if something else is going
on they may be misinterpreted
but obviously we're
talking about in all good
situations or not that an
MI is good that the EKG
change will show the MI and
the biochemical markers will
confirm them and we're
going to talk about a few of
them but the most important
one here is troponin and
CKMB okay myoglobin is
mentioned here it's a rarely
used because it's a marker
that increases rapidly and
decreases rapidly, so that
doesn't really help you.
Whereas troponins, which
are proteins that regulate
the calcium-mediated
contraction of cardiac
and skeletal muscle, are
cardiac-specific, and they
usually rise within two
to four hours when you
have an acute MI, up to
12 hours. They peak at
around a day or two days,
and And the important thing
is that they remain
elevated for 7 to 10 days.
That's important
because when I was in
residency, we didn't
really have troponins.
We had CKMB, which
is a CK isoform.
And those returned to
normal by 72 hours.
So you couldn't
tell if there was an
MI greater than 3
days necessarily.
So the CKMB will rise within
4 hours up to 8 and also
peaks at about a day.
but will return to normal
before troponins turn to
normal and can be helpful in
detecting reinfarction that
occurs after initial MI.
So this is a very important
visual chart of
what I just said.
M stands for the myoglobin
as you can tell it
goes up and down within
a day, not very helpful.
Most places use troponins
and CKMB and troponins as
you can see go with high
really high at about the
same time as CKMB but they
stay high for a long time so
that's why they're more
helpful but CKMB follows a
similar pathway it's just
shorter okay now to recognize
and understand MI we
have to review something
from first year which is
cellular injury and when we
talked about adaptation and
injury and death, we have
to understand what's going
on within the myocyte. So
if you recall, hypoxia or
low oxygen delivery causes
cell injury and that could
be caused by ischemia,
which means decreased
blood flow like
when coronary arteries
are obstructed.
Hypoxemia is a low
partial pressure of oxygen
in the blood and anemia,
which is hemoglobin
loss, which means
decreased oxygen carrying
capacity usually we're
talking here about ischemia
now early on biochemically
if you recall there's
going to be aerobic glycolysis
cessation ATP is stopped
so within seconds and
you'll get accumulation of
breakdown products like
lactic acid and loss of
contractility this is very
early on early on if you recall
changes are still reversible
about 20 minutes this
is 20 to 40 minutes might
be less than that you
can't really see these changes
under a microscope maybe
with an electron microscope
but what does that imply
clinically what that
implies clinically is that
you really have to move fast
to save myocyte cell all
the cells that might so
the more time you taken to
go to the hospital or time
to fibrinolysis or treatment
is going to mean more
tissue loss so it's very
important to try to get to
treatment right away this
is again a review of what
happens when oxygen there's
no there's deprivation
in myocardial hypoxia the
increase in anaerobic
metabolism decreased ATP if
you recall What does that
mean? That means the sodium
-potassium pump is impaired.
And when that happens,
sodium goes into the cell,
and with sodium goes water,
which means there's going
to be edema in the cell.
Extracellularly, potassium
is released, and also later
on, not later on, a few
minutes later, intracellular
calcium is also increased,
which gets going all those
enzymes that destroy the
cells. The increase or the
acidity of the intercellular
hydrogen ion will cause
problems with the nucleus.
You'll start seeing chromatin
clumping and protein
denaturation. Remember the
karyoaxis and all those other
terms that we use. So the
initial phase of any injury,
but we're talking about
the heart now, is reversible.
And the hallmark is
going to be cellular swelling,
another name for edema.
And the swelling of
the rough endoplasmic
reticulum results in
dissociation of the
ribosome and decrease
of protein synthesis.
Then as time goes on, and
like I said, 20-30 minutes,
further damage becomes
irreversible. And that
hallmark is membrane damage.
Okay, the mitochondrial
membrane, the plasma
membrane, and of course with
irreversible injury is
cell death or necrosis.
So this is kind of
important. We're going to go
through the timing of an
infarct histologically and
grossly. Grossly is not
as important. I mean it is
important but can sometimes
not be seen very well. But
I do want to go over the
histopathological changes.
As I said early on in
reversible injury you really
can't see anything under
the microscope but within
a couple hours up to
about four hours you will
get the presence of wavy
fibers and I'm going to
show you pictures of this
in a little bit after about
four to twelve hours
that's when you will see be
able to visually see
coagulant necrosis remember
that the heart will undergo
coagulative necrosis
now what does that mean well
that means that necrosis
will initiate or will
induce inflammation, as
we learned last year. So
we're going to get the
start of a neutrophil
infiltrate at around 24 hours.
So at 12 to 24 hours,
we have coagulative
necrosis, pycnosis
of the nuclei,
very, very pink or red
myocytes because they're dying,
and the neutrophils start
coming in. certainly by one
day two days three days
they will be a definite
infiltration neutrophils they
would be very prominent and
the necrosis will be
prominent now as you go on and
these are not set in stone
these days so it's just three
to seven days it could be
four to seven days it could
be two to you know these
are this is a spectrum so
it's not like day three they
decide to you know this is
an artificial separation
but the next step along is
that macrophages come in
again the neutrophils don't
magically go away on day three
and then all the macrophages
come in it's it is a spectrum
it is um you know it's
on a spectrum so basically
you'll still have neutrophils
but here in three to
seven days the macrophages
come in and as it increase
in macrophages you're going
to be decreasing your
infiltrate of neutrophils. Seven
to ten days is when we're
talking about granulation
tissue. If you remember,
granulation tissue is important
in healing, in scar formation,
and it is made up of
new blood vessels,
macrophages, and collagen or
fibroblasts that that secrete
collagen. So at about a week
you've got granulation
tissue going on and as things
progress the granulation
tissue gets more well formed.
Angiogenesis same thing
as neovascularization two
to eight again this is an
overlap two to eight weeks
you're going to start
scar formation because
collagen is going to be
increased okay. It's not till
one or maybe greater than
two months that you have
a dense collagenous scar
and that's important to
know because after that
time you really can't tell
how you can tell it was
more than two months but
you can't tell anything
else about the MI how long
ago it was. So this
is the myocardial part
histopathological changes
which are important. Now we're
going to look at them a
little bit more closely.
This is normal okay this
is normal histology the
blue arrow is pointing at
an intercalated disc it's
very very very faint but
it's there which are the
discs that help to synchronize
myocyte contraction
by electrical coupling
from the adjoining cells.
So this is all normal
okay you can see
there's some striation
and central nuclei.
Acute reversible changes
between 0 to 30 minutes
we're going to use
that number it again it
could be 20 minutes or
a little bit longer.
You really can't see much
of anything unless you
really go on high power
or basically electron
microscopy, which you won't
do unless it's a study. So
the ischemia will cause
decreased oxidative
phosphorylation, decreased
ATP as we described, and the
sodium potassium pump
fails or doesn't work well,
and therefore sodium goes
into the cell and water
follows. And what you see
here are those myocytes
that are all swollen,
vacuolized, if you will.
Now,
when irreversible damage
starts occurring 30
minutes to about four hours,
you get the presence of
wavy fibers because the
heart is still contracting,
but that area is dead.
So they're kind of being
tugged on and that's
called wavy fiber change.
Four to 12 hours approximately
is not only edema
because you see here you've
got some white spaces that's
the edema but you definitely
have early coaguline
necrosis how do I know this
is necrotic well for one
thing the nuclei are going
away those little blue
spots you see there are black
spots those are interstitial
cells those are not the
myocytes remember those
longitudinal red stripes
are going to have central
nuclei and they're not present
here and the striations
start going away you usually
can't see this grossly
when it's less than 12
hours unless you in the
old days they used to use
something called a stain
called TTC which would stain
normal myocardium really
brick red but the infarcted
area would be pale and
that's because there would
be loss of dehydrogenases.
So early acute MI 24 hours
definitely now you have
the neutrophils the yellow
arrows kind of pointing
to one of them. There's
loss of the cross
striations. There is a
cariolysis that the nuclei are
disappearing basically and
the neutrophils come in.
One to three days now we have
lots and lots of neutrophils.
As the top picture shows
coagulonecrosis is there
because that's what the
neutrophils are attracted to dead
tissue. They're going to
come in to clean up and And
that's what you have. So
this is one to three days.
This is how it would
look like grossly.
Again, gross is a little
bit harder because, you
know, yellow modeling or
yellow center red modeling
is hard to, sometimes
it depends on the
tissue, depends on how
long the person's been
passed away and
things like that. But
this is what's
usually talked about.
Now, after three days, about
three to seven days the
like I said the neutrophils
start leaving and now
we're going to have early
phagocytosis that means
macrophages are coming in
and they're there to clean up
the dead tissue okay they're
in there to as a second
wave as you will as you
know they're not the first
responders like the neutrophils
okay at about a week
to ten days now what we
have here is granulation
tissue granulation tissue
as I mentioned you see red
little spots in here these
are these streaks are blood
vessels and the cellular
stuff is basically
macrophages and tissue that's
going to be forming collagen
on top where it's nice and
pink that's tissue that's
not effective we've got
granulation tissue that's
going on and remember
granulation tissue is the bridge
between necrosis and
healing or scar formation.
In this case because the
heart is permanent tissue
myocytes do not regenerate
and they will form a scar.
So after two weeks it's
healing has started to occur
you can see there's a
light paleness in the upper
right corner there that
is increased collagen and
the cells are going to be
decreased in cellularity
because they're gone and
you'll start forming a scar
that will be mature by one
month or two months and
in this picture really
the upper right of the
picture is what's showing
the collagen and the left you
still have myocytes that
are present with nuclei.
Okay so by two months dense
collagenous scar and here
we go this is what I'm
talking about pale pale pale
okay so at one to two
months is when we get this I
think I can use this
marker because every time
I do I can't I can't
advance the the slides okay
contraction bands are
something to know about
when we have something
called reperfusion injury.
Contraction bands can be
mistaken sometimes for
intercalated discs. They're
not. They're very very pink
or red horizontal transverse
bands and they're made
up of hyper contracted
sarcomeres and that's
associated with the reperfusion
injury meaning when blood
is is perfused back into
an area that's dead it'll
be seen mostly at the
margin of involved it
represents the hyper contraction
of the muscles due to
massive calcium influx
across the plasma membranes.
In the absence of ATP
sarcomeres can't relax
so they get stuck in this
kind of agonal tetanic
state that's what
contraction band necrosis is.
Okay and here's a picture
of again like like I
said it looks a lot
like intercalated discs
but it is not. These are
irregular dark pink wavy
contraction bands that
you get from reperfusion,
injury, or around the
edge of an infarct.
Okay now the important thing
is complications of MI.
What can happen if someone
survives an MI? And we're
going to go through all
these. These are all important
and they all occur at
different times or may occur
at different times. So
we're going to go through
shock, arrhythmia, acute
etc. Not necessarily in this
order but we're go through
each of them. But first
before that let's have a
question. A 55 year old man
sudden onset a severe substernal
chest pain radiates to
the neck. He's afebrile
but he's tachycardic. He's
hyperventilating. His blood
pressure is low. There are
no murmurs heard. The
patient undergoes a emergent
coronary angiography and it
shows a thrombotic occlusion
of the left circumflex
artery and 50 to 70 percent
narrowing in the proximal
circumflex and anterior
descending arteries. So
which of the following
complications of this disease
is most likely to occur within
one hour of these events?
Now I haven't talked about
complications yet but what
you're going to find is
that most complications take
a couple days to a little
bit longer except for A
ventricular fibrillation.
That is the number one
cause of death on the way to
the hospital because it's
going to happen within an hour
or within two hours or even
within 24 hours. So that
is an important thing to
remember that a person can
die of ventricular fibrillation
and arrhythmia within
hours of the MI which is
again why it's important to
get them to the hospital.
So it is a major source of
pre-hospital mortality and
it may be due to anatomic
interruption of perfusion
to the structures in the
conduction pathway because
of you know there's going to
be toxic metabolic products
ion concentrations are
going to be abnormal if
somebody had an MI in the past
that could be scar tissue
that could cause arrhythmia
and again it usually occurs
four to 24 hours after an
MI and one of the reasons
why is because these coronary
arteries RCA LAD as shown
here on the right they
perfuse or they feed the
nodes the SA node is most 70
% of patients is the RCA
the AV node as well and all
the other you know conduction
pathways so that's why
that's important okay so what
can happen afterwards well
within a couple days you
can get acute fibrinous
pericarditis, and that's
because neutrophils are going
to be recruited to the
dead site, dying cells, and
enzymes are released. These
are metalloproteinases, and
they degrade collagen. They
irritate the pericardium,
and that's what causes acute
fibrinous pericarditis.
This generally will
resolve over the next
few days, and again,
it's most likely to
occur about two to
three days after an MI.
Now pericarditis will show
up as a pericardial, maybe
a pericardial fusion. You
will hear muffled heart
sounds. There will be a low
blood pressure associated
with pulsus paradoxus,
and pulsus paradoxus is an
abnormal drop in blood pressure
greater than 10, systolic
blood pressure greater
than 10, when the patient
inspires. There will be
neck pain distension the
chest x-ray may show water
bottle configuration and I
have a picture of that and
very importantly you'll
hear a friction rub a
pericardial friction which is
scratchy and it's best heard
when you ask the patient
to lean forward and that's
for obvious reasons because
then the pericardium is
up against the chest wall.
It commonly presents
with sharp pain and
that pain is going
to be worsened by
breathing in but
relieved by sitting up.
So this is what we mean
by the water bottle
configuration in acute
fibrinous pericarditis.
Now there's another pericarditis
that can occur. It's
very important to realize
this is different. This is
called Dressler syndrome
and this pericarditis is an
autoimmune fibrinous
pericarditis which can occur two
weeks or two to two months
post my and the reason why is
because it's autoimmune and
you need autoantibodies to
develop which is why they
don't doesn't happen within
days it has it takes at
least two weeks so the
autoantibodies are directed
against the pair the damaged
pericardial antigens and you're
going to have the similar
symptoms but it's going
to be later now this is
catastrophic absolutely
catastrophic um very few people
survive this this is a
myocardial rupture the heart has
basically perforated if you
will uh it hasn't it's it's
it's blown up in a sense the
myocardial rupture usually
occurs around three to
seven days again it could be
two to six three to seven
the point being that that's
when the myocardium is softest
that's when the granulation
tissue is there coaguline
necrosis the neutrophil
infiltrate etc that area
is weak and soft at around
that time so at about a week
or even you know like three
or four days this is when
there's a danger of course
it doesn't thankfully this
doesn't always happen but
it can happen now the arrow
here is showing where the
rupture is here and all that
blood was trapped inside
the pericardial sac causing
cardiac tamponade and here
we've cleared this picture
is showing the rupture, the
arrows going through it.
We've cleared out the blood,
but I want to talk a little
bit about cardiac tamponade.
That's compression of the
heart by blood that has
been accumulated because of
the rupture, and it's in the
pericardium. So cardiac
output will be decreased, and
you will have equilibration
diastatic pressure in all
four chambers. You also
may find something called
Beck's triad, low blood
pressure, distending neck veins,
distant heart sounds.
Again, that all makes sense
because the blood is accumulating
in the pericardial sac.
The heart rate will be
increased, pulsus paradoxus,
and kusmosine, which
kusmosine is a paradoxical
rise in JVP, jugular venous
pressure on inspiration.
And the EKG will
show low voltage
QRS and electrical alternates.
Now we're going to talk
about the concept of false
and true aneurysms now I
don't want you to get too
involved in this people get
very confused by this the
newest edition of Robbins
doesn't even go into false
aneurysms but let me just
describe it and I really want
you to learn what a true
aneurysm is so what if the
rupture if the person
has a rupture of the left
ventricle or the ventricle
is not complete if it's not
complete then the the left
ventricular free wall is going
to be held in check by a
thrombus, and that will
be a plug, if you will, in
the hole in the myocardium.
And so even though the
myocardium is gone, epicardium
and inherent parietal
pericardium will form a false
wall, which is why it's
called the false aneurysm.
Now let's talk, let's
move on to true aneurysms,
but before we do,
question break. A 58
-year-old man suffered
a myocardial infarction
involving the apex of
the left ventricle.
Six months later, the
echocardiogram shows the
development of a bulge, a
ventricular bulge that does
not contract during systole.
So right then and there,
there's something
abnormal, and that is an
aneurysm. It's sticking out.
It's a weakened area. It
doesn't go along with the
contraction of the heart.
The patient then
suffers a massive stroke
and suddenly dies.
Which of the following
would be an expected
finding at autopsy?
So looking at the choices,
remembering why stroke
occurs, the answer is D, as in
David, mural thrombus. That
area of aneurysm, the true
aneurysm, is going to be
dilated area, which is going
to be static meaning the
blood is not moving if you
recall in a laminar flow
it's kind of an eddy if you
will like in a lake and because
of the stasis blood will
tend to coagulate and you
form a thrombus and that
will then embolize to the
brain and causing a stroke so
that is a true ventricular
anerogen shown here what
you see the aropoenia is a
myocardial the ventricular
wall that is really really
thinned out and weakened it's
it's really the my it is
that the ventricular wall
and here is a cross section
and it bulges out as it's
shown here and so this will
become an area where blood
fills in and it's an area
of stasis and that may cause
a clot, a thrombus, which
can embolize to the brain.
Here's another picture
of it. Here's one
from the outside. The
circle is around it
and another one that's
a different section.
This is a late complication
of a myocardial
part. We're talking
weeks to months after.
It does not involve
communication between the
left ventricle and the
pericardium because that
would be something that
would happen in the
rupture in which you
would have the cardiac
tamponade. So and in and
of itself it usually does
not rupture despite how
thin and weak it looks.
Another type of rupture is
the papillary muscle rupture
that leads to incompetent
mitral valve. So you get
mitral regurg, the blood
will back up into the lungs
with a transdation of fluid,
a shortness of breath,
and a murmur that you will
hear throughout the system.
The posterior medial left
ventricular papillary
muscle is the one that's
most susceptible only
because it has the most
precarious blood supply.
So right here that you
see the blue arrow is
where there's a rupture
of the papillary muscle.
Again, This would probably
occur around this, you
know, if it's going
to occur like the left
ventricular wall rupture,
it's going to be where the
tissue is soft, and
that's usually, you know,
three to seven days.
The ventricular septum can
also rupture. There's a
pencil, it looks like,
going through this. The
septum rupture is analogous
to the left ventricular
free wall rupture, but it's
a different consequence.
Because now you will have
left ventricular pressures,
blood is going to go into
the right, ventricle blood
is shunted because of the
pressure difference, and the
patient will present with
right-sided heart failure,
JVD, and pedal edema,
and you will hear
a loud systolic
murmur at the left
sternal border, which
is transeptal flow.
Okay, and also,
very importantly,
is congestive heart failure,
left ventricular failure.
contractile dysfunction.
So if more than 40% of the
left ventricle is infarcted,
that's a pretty major amount
of the left ventricle,
then your contractility will
be down and hypertension
will occur, coronary
perfusion pressure goes
down, and the heart basically
backs up, if you will.
You have severely
decreased cardiac
output, hypertension,
and you'll have
edema, pulmonary edema
and heart failure.
This picture is more put
in here only to talk a
little bit about pulmonary
edema which is I know another
topic in another lecture
but in pulmonary edema
this is not normal lung
I hope you recognize that
it's this light pink tissue
that's fluid in the lung
that's like the person
is drowning in their own
you know in a backup fluid
and the brown stuff the
real brown stuff that's
hemocytorin-laden macrophages
which are basically old
blood that they go in and
they try to eat up you
know what's in there which
is blood basically those
are heart failure cells so
so this is a nice overview
of what we've talked about
the mi that can lead to a
ventricular thrombus and
embolized to the brain
or you can have loss of
contractility and cardiogenic
shock congestive heart
failure. The necrosis
itself can occur and cause
ventricular wall rupture in
cardiac tamponade or papillary
muscle rupture or
ventricular septal rupture or
pericardial inflammation.
And that will be either
Dressler's Kitts syndrome or
if not Dressler's syndrome,
acute fibrinous
pericarditis, which
occurs before that
if it would occur.
I don't talk much about
treatment and I'm going to
defer to the clinicians
but of course you want to
limit the thrombosis give
oxygen uh nitrates uh to
vasodilate beta blockers
to slow the heart rate and
ace inhibitors to decrease
the left ventricle dilatation
and of course really you
want to get them to the
hospital for angioplasty
fibrinolysis is not as I
mean if that's all you have
that's what you use but
that also puts it at risk
of bleeding but it does
open up but the angioplasty
is much more effective.
Finally this is a question
is basically the last
question is kind of complex
but go let's go through
it slowly. A 52 year old
man with a history of
diabetes hypertension has
pain in his left arm and
shoulder for the past two
hours. Then over six hours
he develops shortness of
breath which continues
for two days so it's been
going on now for two days
but now on day three he
finally goes to the doctor and
he has a normal temperature
but the pulse is 82 the
respirations are 18 which
is a little bit normal but
a little bit on the high
going to a high blood pressure
is high because he has
hypertension so they do lab
studies at the time and the
creatinine kindness serum
levels are normal but the
troponin level is increased
and that's very important
because the troponin level
indicates here that there
has been an infarct. Now the
fact that the creatin kinase
is normal tells you that
at least three days has
passed or three days have
passed because if you remember
that chart from before
CKMB goes down before troponin.
So the patient is admitted
to the hospital and
continues to have dyspnea for
the next three days on day
seven after the initial
onset of shoulder pain he
has a cardiac arrest meaning
just that his heart stopped
and he doesn't survive and
they show an autopsy
shows a large transmural
infarction of the left
anterior free wall
with rupture and
hemopericardium so cardiac
tamponade occurred
obviously and he died.
So which statement
of following is true?
The myocardial infarction
did not develop until
day five or six after the
episode of shoulder pain.
Well we know that there was
troponin levels elevated
on day three so it did develop
before five six so that
is false. The normal CK
level on day three excludes
the possibility of an MI
within the preceding 72 hours?
No, because we know
that goes down, CKMB
goes down, and the
troponin will be elevated.
Let's go to D. A
CKMB level would have
detected an acute
MI on day three.
Not really, because if
you go back to that chart,
you'll see that the CKMB
is usually down by day
three, below threshold, so
it would not necessarily
have detected. And the
patient had a second MI,
which caused a myocardial
rupture on day seven?
No, that probably is not
true because myocardial
ruptures usually happen,
well, it could be day
seven, but in this case,
the best answer is C,
that the whole thing,
the patient had an acute
MI on the day he developed
the shoulder pain,
okay? The fact that you
cannot convince me that
he had a second MI and
the myocardial rupture
occurred on day, may have
occurred on day seven,
but not from a second
MI, but from the first,
okay? Because cardiac arrest
does not mean MI, it just
means the heart stops.
So the cardiac arrest was
because of the cardiac
tamponade. I hope that's clear.
What type of necrosis does
occur following an MI?
And I hope you all know
the answer to that is
coagulant necrosis. And what
type of cells infiltrate
the myocardium between
one to three days or three
to seven days post-MI?
again the one to three days
would be neutrophils
because they come in first
as they go down macrophages
go up and the macrophages
should be the most in
three to seven days as
angiogenesis occurs and
you have granulation tissue
this is a summary slide
again the histopathology
here is a little bit
important they like asking
about that and these
are my references thank
you for your attention and
if you have any questions
please email me and
I'll be happy to answer.